<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lars Spreng</title>
    <link>https://larsspreng.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://larsspreng.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Lars Spreng</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://larsspreng.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Lars Spreng</title>
      <link>https://larsspreng.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Combining p-Values for Multivariate Predictive Ability Testing</title>
      <link>https://larsspreng.github.io/publication/combpvaljbes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://larsspreng.github.io/publication/combpvaljbes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Risk Indicator for the UK Real Estate Market</title>
      <link>https://larsspreng.github.io/project/re_stu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://larsspreng.github.io/project/re_stu/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Macroeconomic Management on Becoming an African Oil Exporter</title>
      <link>https://larsspreng.github.io/project/oil_ms/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://larsspreng.github.io/project/oil_ms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper provides analysis of the macroeconomic management implications of becoming
an exporter of oil, taking the case of Ghana and applying to Uganda as a prospective
exporter. The paper proceeds in two steps. First, we construct a Dynamic Stochastic
General Equilibrium (DSGE) model of a primary commodity exporting developing
country calibrated to Ghana and Uganda and simulate the impulse response to shocks to
the oil price and oil production. Second, using parameters from the DSGE model to obtain
priors for parameter values, we use a Structural Vector Autoregressive (SVAR) with
monthly data over 2001 to 2019 to estimate the response to oil shocks as an importer for
both countries and as an exporter for Ghana after 2010. The DSGE results suggest that
although an oil price shock generates appreciation and initially output falls, there are
reductions in interest rates and inflation and ultimately output increases. The larger the oil
sector the greater the appreciation and inflationary effects, but output rises more quickly
and there are larger increases in wages and taxes. The SVAR results for Ghana when
exporting suggest an initial depreciation in response to an oil price shock, with a reduction
in inflation, but the immediate negative output response slowly turns positive (and becomes
consistent with the DSGE). When Ghana and Uganda are importers, oil price shocks
generate appreciation, mild inflation and interest rate reductions, so although output
declines initially it rises after a year and this persists. The analysis suggests that the adoption
of inflation targeting, in conjunction with an improved monitoring of macroeconomic
developments, has mitigated the effects of oil price shocks on domestic variables in Ghana
and Uganda.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exchange Rates and Macroeconomic Fundamentals -- Evidence of Instabilities from Time-Varying Factor Loadings</title>
      <link>https://larsspreng.github.io/project/fx_hmsu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://larsspreng.github.io/project/fx_hmsu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We examine the relationship between exchange rates and macroeconomic fundamentals using a two-step maximum likelihood estimator through which we compute time-varying factor loadings. Factors are obtained as principal components, extracted from a large macro-dataset. Using 14 currencies over 1995–2018, we show that the loadings on the factors vary considerably over time with frequent sign changes. Allowing for time-varying loadings increases the percentage of explained variation in exchanges rates by an order of magnitude. Accounting for instabilities improves the predictive ability of the model globally and locally during crises, and yields better forecast of sign changes in exchange rates.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aid and Exchange Rates in sub-Saharan Africa --  No More Dutch Disease?</title>
      <link>https://larsspreng.github.io/project/aid_rsm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://larsspreng.github.io/project/aid_rsm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Given the significant inflows of foreign aid to sub-Saharan Africa (SSA) the possibility
of Dutch Disease has been a concern. Most macroeconomic models predict that aid
inflows, especially if large and/or unanticipated (shocks), will lead to an appreciation of
the real exchange rate and undermine the competitiveness of the economy. Empirical
evidence is inconclusive, but a common presumption is that aid has been associated with
Dutch Disease effects in SSA. Previous empirical studies rely on annual data and few
include data since the mid-2000s. This paper focuses on the more recent period employing
monthly time series data for ten countries over 2001 to 2017 to estimate a structural VAR.
For the majority of countries aid has no or a minimal effect on the real exchange rate;
there is evidence of a significant real appreciation in only two countries. Additional
analysis shows that commodity export prices are a more important determinant of the real
exchange rate, with an effect on average twice that of aid. The paper conjectures that the
absence of a Dutch Disease effect since the 2000s is due to a declining level of aid inflows
and improved macroeconomic management.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://larsspreng.github.io/admin/config.yml</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://larsspreng.github.io/admin/config.yml</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nothing here yet</title>
      <link>https://larsspreng.github.io/post/getting-started/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://larsspreng.github.io/post/getting-started/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;example-post&#34;&gt;Example Post&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example post&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
